Ivan Franco

R&D Director and Researcher

Montreal, QC, Canada Phone: +1 438 832 9610

Email: ivan.almeida.franco@gmail.com
Portfolio: https://ifranco.github.io/

LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/ivan-almeida-franco

PROFILE

R&D director with 10+ years of experience in research, development and strategic management of **interactive products and technologies**. Clients and partners such as Coca-Cola, Adidas, Unilever, Santander, Microsoft, Dell, ESA and Philips. Recognized thought-leader in human-computer interaction and audiovisual technologies.

EXPERTISE

- R&D management (strategic, technical and operational).
- Ideation, prototyping and product development.
- Intellectual property, licensing and partnerships.
- Team management through Agile principles.
- Worked across teams with Production, Sales, Marketing and VPs.
- Excellent communicator and consultant.
- Skills in HCI, UX, XR, user-centered design, audio, programming and electronics.

ACHIEVEMENTS

- R&D director and principal technologist for award-winning company YDreams.
- PhD in music technology.
- Peer-reviewed publishing and co-author of several patents.
- Business development in Silicon Valley with partners and clients like Dell, HP and IBM.
- Participation in VC and IPO operations for YDreams and its spin-offs.
- Development of AR experiences for Canesta and Primesense, later acquired by Microsoft to create the Kinect controller.
- Winner of Best Tech Demo at the Augmented Reality Expo 2010 (ARE 2010).
- Guest Speaker at ISE DOOH Business Conference, TEDx, EComm, OFFF, SXSW, ARE, Screenmedia Expo, Berklee College of Music, IBM Research, 6 Sight, NIME, Merging

- 2011, Pecha Kucha, Future Places, GEAR, Upgrade!, Art Futura, Zeppelin Festival and many other events.
- Winner of several awards and scholarships, including the 2010 Personality of the Year Award by the Portuguese Association for the Promotion of Multimedia and Digital Society.

WORK EXPERIENCE

2014 - Present / Lecturer and Associate Researcher / McGill University

- Research and development of digital musical instruments using embedded computing.
- Creator and principal developer of <u>Prynth</u>, an open source hardware and software **framework with hundreds of users**.
- New Media Production lecturer, teaching DSP and interactivity implemented in Max.

2002 - 2013 / **R&D Director** / YDreams

- Started as a research associate working on the creative use of interactive audiovisual systems and alternative user interfaces.
- **Grew the startup from 10 people to 200**, attracting a capital investment of €16M through innovation.
- Led all technical and strategic management of R&D in the company, managing a yearly budget of around €1M and a team of 25+ researchers and managers.
- Built an **IP portfolio** with several patents and trademarks used in our products and licensed to partners.
- Our research team also worked closely with the **product development** team to ensure an efficient integration of new technologies and features.
- Worked on spin-offs, creating **business plans**, raising **VC capital** and participating in IPO operations (<u>YDreams Global</u>, <u>Ynvisible</u>).

2001 - 2002 / Lecturer and Researcher / Pompeu Fabra University

- Development of interactive music systems.
- Music composition and production lecturer.

EDUCATION

- PhD in Music Technology (McGill University).
- Master in Digital Arts (Pompeu Fabra University).
- BSc in Engineering (New University of Lisbon).